My name is
temple grandin.
I'm not like
other people.
I think in pictures
and i connect them.
There she is!
Temple!
It's hot!
Come on, dear.
You're holding up
the other passengers!
I can see the heat!
Temple!
Do people live here?
The wolf is growling
And the man with the shotgun
says to illya kuryakin,
"would you like for me
to open the gate?"
I'm sorry, temple,
you lost me.
"The man from U.N.C.L.E."--
"The gazebo in the maze."
The wolf is growling
And the man with the shotgun
says to illya kuryakin,
Both:
would you like for me
to open the gate?
"Would you like for me
to open the gate?"
You okay?
Aunt ann,
what is this place?
Ann:
just holding pens.
You don't have those
on the east coast, huh?
Is this where they
slaughter them?
Yes, it is.
Temple:
"would you like for me
to open the gate?"
"Would you like for me
- Yes. Yes, please.
Open the gate,
please, temple?
- Would you like for me
to open that gate?
- Yes!
Man:
that's it!
Ann:
come on, temple.
Temple?
Man:
come on, git!
Here they come.
- Ann: temple made it okay.
- Say hi to your uncle mike.
- Hi, temple.
I-- I just been
tellin' billy here
All about
our summer visitor.
- Are you a cowboy?
- Excuse my niece.
That's not how
we greet people, temple.
You know better than that.
Hello, i'm temple.
It's very nice
to meet you.
Hello, i'm temple.
It's very nice
to meet you.
Billy:
nice to meet you too.
Ma'am.
Thanks for this.
I'll replace it tomorrow.
Yeah. No rush.
I got spares.
Uh.
Oh!
Do you get
"the man from u.N.C.L.E."?
Let me show
you your room.
These okay here?
Oh, and i put
all my science fiction
books there.
How do i know
this is my room?
Because we say so.
It's your room.
Okay?
Okay.
So, temple,
y-You excited
about college?
That's something.
- Thank you.
- I can't eat that.
I have colitis.
I get it from nervousness.
- I eat pudding and jell-O.
- I know.
Your mom said.
- So you didn't answer
mike's question.
Are you excited
about going to college?
I want to stay
in high school.
I like my
science teacher.
Dr. Carlock's very smart
and he's been to college.
So i don't understand why
i have to move to learn what
he probably already knows.
The desert spoons
and teaspoons go in
different sections.
I did that.
You know, your uncle
can't tell them apart.
And sometimes
i can't either.
They're different.
Yes, they are.
i think it's time
for bed, young lady.
We get up with
the rooster around here.
- You got everything?
- This is my room.
Yes, it is.
- So good night.
- I don't want you
to do that.
I'm sorry.
I forgot--
No hugs.
Good night then.
Hello?
Ann:
did i wake you?
Of course not.
- Man: who is it?
- It's ann!
Guess what i found
balled up in the bottom
of temple's closet?
A lovely summer frock
she didn't want?
It's taken me an age
to iron it.
I'll mail it
in the morning.
If you couldn't get her
to pack it,
I'm not sure
i can get her to wear it.
The other one came off
the minute she arrived.
How is she?
She's good.
Tell me.
she, uh--
She got tense when mike
mentioned college,
But-- No, but then
she calmed down
And she went off to bed
just fine.
Stop worrying.
Temple's my job
for the summer.
Worry about the others.
I'm sure she's gonna
have a great time.
You do remember,
though,
Something's
gonna set her off.
- Ann: temple?
Temple!
Temple, i could really use
a hand here!
So any idea what
your major might be?
Science--
Probably psychology.
Well, you don't have to
decide just yet, do you?
It's better
than boarding school.
- That's great.
- Lots of choices.
- Danny's looking at you.
He can see all around
without moving his head.
- So how do you know
where he's looking?
- His ears.
He points his ears
where he's looking.
See?
He's lookin' at you.
And he's lookin'
at those cowboys.
See?
Now i got his attention.
Now he's looking at me.
You're right.
- How'd you figure that out?
- There you go!
What are they doing?
Temple:
what is this thing?
It holds her still
so billy can inoculate her.
What happened to it?
It calmed down.
They just like it.
It gentles 'em.
Billy:
stand still
and they'll come to you.
Won't harm you.
Just curious.
Can't help themselves.
Ann: are you worried
about keeping up with
the other students?
No.
I'm not stupid.
I didn't say
you were.
- Is it moving away from home?
- Hold it straighter.
- Why don't you want
to go to college?
People.
I don't understand people.
At least the people
at school know i don't
understand them
And some of them
are my friends anyway.
What don't you
understand?
Girls get all goofy
over boys.
They talk about
silly pop groups and clothes
and say things like,
"Why are you so grumpy?"
When i'm happy.
And i say, "i'm happy."
And they say, "well, you
don't look happy."
And i say, "well,
can't you see i'm thinking?
And can't you see i'm sad?"
And i don't know
what they're talking about.
- What do you look like
when you're happy?
- Like this.
- No. That's not what
you looked like
When you were telling me about
"the man from u.N.C.L.E."
You looked like this--
That's funny lookin'.
- Ann: happy.
And that's you angry.
Angry.
- Happy.
I'm happy in that one.
I'd say more satisfied.
Satisfied.
Ann:
maria, can you
give me a hand here?
- Temple!
Temple!
close it on me.
- Temple, let's
get you out of--
- Close it on me!
- Don't be silly!
- Please!
Close the sides.
Please!
Harder!
More!
Did you see temple's
handiwork at the gate?
Isn't that
the darndest thing?
- Aw.
- Hi.
- Oh.
- Hi, darlin'.
All these years
ann's been bugging me.
Like i could ever
come up with that!
Is that it?
- Is that what
temple's been using?
- Yes, it is.
I know, it looks horrible,
but it helps her.
I-I'll go find temple.
Temple!
That's mine.
That's temple's.
She's had
a great summer.
You won't believe
the things she's fixed.
She's wonderful
with the cattle.
Yeah.
I-- I appreciate that.
I should warn you,
she has her mind
set on staying.
That's not an option.
Ann.
I'm sorry.
I didn't mean
to attack you,
Especially when
you've been so generous
all summer.
Temple?
Temple.
- Temple!
How was your trip, mother?
You made good time.
It was long.
Thank you for asking.
You ready
for college?
I think i'd rather
stay here.
We've talked
about this.
Sweetheart,
you're gonna be fine.
No one expected it.
It's nothin' short
of a miracle.
It's a miracle!
Temple, this way.
- Can i get that for you?
- Thank you.
- * in a young
girl's heart... *
* a chance to be free
whenever it starts *
* and it's magic
if the music is groovy *
* it makes you feel happy
like an old-Time movie *
* believe in the magic...
- Ohh!
224.
This is you.
- I don't have a roommate.
- No no no.
Your roommate is coming
in another couple of weeks.
Remember?
Everyone else
has a roommate!
Well then, why don't you just
think of it as a chance to
settle in, sweetheart?
- Then i'll go back home!
- Temple.
I know that this
is strange and new,
But you're going
to be all right.
I don't want to
stay here!
Try and stay calm.
It's all right.
Try and calm down,
all right?
I'm going to give you
a moment to yourself.
- What's wrong?
- Is she all right?
Man's voice:
interested in playing
with other children?
No, not really.
Plays with toys,
dolls?
Eustacia:
she loves to rip things.
And no speech yet
at the age of?
Four.
She's four.
No, not yet.
I'm sure it's just
a phase, but, uh--
Your child
is clearly autistic.
Autistic.
- I'm not familiar--
- She's an infantile
schizophrenic.
Le?
Infant
Um, so-- So when would
she grow out of it?
I mean, what's
the next step for--
We generally recommend
an institution.
Oh.
For how long?
I'm not sure
i would like that.
I really--
I-- I wouldn't want to
miss her first words.
She probably
will never speak.
And i'm afraid there is
no course of treatment.
I'm talking about
institutionalization.
But, um--
I mean, she-- She was
a perfectly normal baby
And then later
she changed.
So i need to know
how, why.
i'm not sure you'd un--
Perhaps if you had
your husband call me.
My husband is a
very busy man and i
graduated from harvard,
- So why don't you try me?
- I'm sorry.
It's been suggested
that it may be
A lack of bonding
with the mother--
That at a crucial phase,
the mother was cold, aloof,
When the child most needed
physical affection.
But that is not
what happened.
We have another child
and she is not like this
And i did not do
anything different.
Temple rejects me.
I-- I want to hug her
and she won't let me.
I'm supposed
to have done this.
Well, then i can undo it.
You just tell me
what to do.
- Doctor: as i said,
I recommend
institutionalization.
Here is a list of facilities
that we recommend.
Dah-Og.
Temple.
Dog.
Cah-At.
Cat.
Temple, try.
Mah-Me.
Mom--
I know you can hear me.
All right.
I think mommy needs
a five-Minute break.
Okay.
Avez-Vous lu la page,
mile grandin?
No. I don't want
to study french.
I want to learn science.
Read the page, please.
Read it.
And what did it say?
"Jean-Paul sartre nait
le 21 juin 1905, a paris;
Fils unique,
il vient d'une famille
bourgeoise:
- Son pere est polytechni"--
- You--
You learned it?
I just looked at it.
Then i have the page in my mind
and can read off the page.
I see pictures
and connect them.
I-- I only eat
jell-O and yogurt.
I-I only-- I only eat
jell-O and yogurt!
Excuse me?
I'm your roommate.
What are you doing?
It's a machine
i just made.
It feels like a hug.
Do you want a hug?
It feels really good.
So when you got in
your machine,
Did it make you
feel like a cow?
No, i didn't feel
like a cow.
But it gave you
pleasure.
It made me feel good,
gentle.
- The hug made you
feel good.
- Yes.
But you don't like
to be touched by people.
No.
Do you like
to touch yourself?
Touchin' myself's okay.
But when the squeeze
machine touches you,
- It feels better?
- Yes.
It gives you release?
Yes, there is release.
But i need it!
- I built it! It's mine!
- What's all the noise?
- Wait! Stop it!
- Pervert.
- Man: got it?
- Man ã‚â£2: yeah, i got it.
Okay.
23 hours,
59 minutes and four,
Three, two, one,
zero hours, mr. Solo!
Guard: hey!
What are you doing?
Stop!
I said stop!
She says she's not going back
after spring break
Unless she can
take it with her.
- Are you still there?
- Yes.
And i really don't think
it's a good idea.
- It works for her.
It's everything
we've been struggling
to get away from.
They were perfectly clear:
no devices in her room.
Could there be
a better way
To mark her as a weirdo
and an oddball?
Just let us try,
okay?
So that's it.
Okay!
Temple:
it makes me gentle.
Ann:
she's a different person
after just 15 minutes.
- A different person?
How can you explain that?
I can't explain
why the machine works,
but i know it's not sexual.
As temple says,
it calms her.
Look, all this does
is to convince me
That we're not equipped to deal
with ms. Grandin's needs.
It makes her
a better student.
She's able to concentrate,
to interact with others
more easily.
This isn't
very scientific.
- There is no
empirical evidence--
- I can do an experiment.
I can-- I can see how
it works on other people.
I can measure heart rates.
I-- I think it'll work
on everyone.
Let's talk frankly.
I'm not sure you can
get anything from being
at franklin pierce.
Listen to what she's saying.
She wants to do her own
science experiment,
Something that you can evaluate
in her psychology course.
I have a pen
and a clipboard.
Time.
Do you feel:
a, claustrophobic;
B, constricted;
C, no different;
D, comfortable;
E, relaxed?
What was the one
before last?
D, comfortable.
Yes, i'm quite
comfortable.
- Okay.
No different.
A, claustrophobic!
I guess i feel relaxed?
Very relaxed.
Boy:
"f" for "freak."
Hello? Hampshire
country school?
I need to speak
to dr. Carlock!
Receptionist:
dr. Carlock? Yes.
Please hold.
* if i had a bell
* i'd ring it
in the morning *
in the evening *
* all over this land
* i'd ring out danger
- * i'd ring out warning...
- Piggy piggy piggy.
* i'd ring out love between
my brothers and sisters *
* all over this land.
- You're such a good boy.
- Man: oh, please,
here, take this.
I'll take these.
Welcome.
Uh, excuse the mess.
We just had a staff meeting.
Oh, good.
They're here.
Um, temple grandin,
i would like you to meet,
uh, mr. Hodges.
He is our, uh,
mathematics teacher.
Eustacia:
temple, come here.
Hello, i'm temple.
It's very nice to meet you.
This is mademoiselle davide.
She is our french teacher.
Hello, i'm temple,
it's very nice to meet you.
Davide:
bonjour, mademoiselle.
Hi, i'm dr. Carlock.
I teach science.
- Are you a scientist?
- Temple.
Hello, i'm temple,
it's very nice to meet you.
- Are you a scientist?
- I used to work for n.A.S.A.
Mm-Hmm.
Temple's very interested
in science.
- Oh!
- I'd like to meet
belka and strelka.
They're the first dogs
to come back from
space alive.
- That's right, in--
Sputnik v, august 20th, 1960.
- Sputnik v, august 20th, 1960.
Eustacia:
we're changing schools
mid-Term
Because temple's
been expelled.
I'm sorry, why was
she expelled, again?
Hitting another child
with a book.
There's no excuse,
But i will say this
in her defense--
I have never seen her strike
unless she's been provoked.
And other children have
taunted and bullied
her constantly.
They make fun of her
Because she doesn't
understand their jokes.
She spins
to comfort herself.
She talks fast,
often too fast,
And she talks
repetitively
And then the children
called her a tape recorder.
She'll go into
a panic attack
And then they make
fun of that too.
Excuse me.
When was she
diagnosed autistic?
She was four,
But i sometimes wonder
if that's correct.
Why do you say that?
You've seen her--
She's bright.
- We have a lot of experience
With children
with special needs,
emotional problems,
Neuro-Behavioral issues
that we've made a number...
- I think that because of--
- I'm so sorry.
I really have wasted
your time.
I just can't do
this to her.
Mrs. Grandin.
Mrs. Grandin!
Mrs. Grandin, please!
Can i speak with you
for a moment, please?
Mrs. Grandin,
you don't strike me
As the sort of person
who would abuse
their child
Or, uh, or deny them
love and care--
- Now you wait.
I have done everything
that i can for temple
And if it isn't
good enough,
Then it just isn't
good enough.
But you cannot
to begin to imagine
the-- The-- The chaos,
The upheavals,
the tantrums,
and the pain--
Her pain.
Uh, you seem
to be acting
As if you have done
something wrong,
When--
When it's obvious
You've done
everything right.
I-- I think
she's terrific.
I know
it's difficult
When, um, as parents,
we want our children
To be everything
we hoped for them to be
And, if they're not,
we think it's our
fault and--
And that there's never
ever anybody out there
Who understands what
we're going through
That-- Uh, it makes you
feel alone, right?
Um, mrs. Grandin, i'm not,
uh, an admissions person.
I-- I just teach science,
But i feel
that this school
Might be the right place
for your daughter.
I-- I'd love
to have her here.
The doctors wanted me
to institutionalize her.
I don't know.
Just dumping her
at a boarding school,
It just feels like
another way to give her up.
Carlock:
but it's-- It's not.
It's just the first step
In getting her out
into the world.
And--
And, i know
you saw the children
making fun of her
And, uh, you want
to protect her.
Yeah,
of course i do.
Yeah, what parent
doesn't want to?
But at some point,
she's going to hit
life head on.
And trust me,
we-- We know how
different she is.
Different,
not less.
but not less.
You watch.
You'll--
You'll make friends and
you're gonna ride horses.
- Okay?
- Okay.
Okay.
Woman:
what are you doing in
with chestnut?!
No one is to go near
that horse!
Can he be my horse?
He likes being hugged.
I want to ride him!
You'll ride.
Just not chestnut.
"Le pain est
un aliment de base
Dans de nombreuses
societes humaines."
il est.
Il est.
No, say, "il est."
- Il est.
Well, why are so many
fish in france?!
french fish!
French fish!
Excellent work,
temple.
Really excellent work.
- French fish!
french fish!
- Oh!
- Hey! What happened here?
She hit him
for no reason!
Temple.
Come on, let's go.
- And he's done it before!
- Stop. Stop. Temple, stop.
Temple, tim will be punished
for what he did, but you
cannot hit people.
You understand that?
- Good.
And to really get
that through to you,
You will not ride
for two weeks.
- But that's not fair!
- Two weeks.
Man:
no no. There's--
There's nothing there.
And he's been like this
for three hours?
I don't think there's anything
anybody could have done.
I'll send the boy
around with the truck.
Can you do that?
I'll take care
of it, dad.
Temple?
Where do they go?
I don't know.
Um, heaven,
Maybe.
Uh, somewhere.
Temple, when animals
and people die,
They stay with us
in our minds.
We can still see them.
So i think it would best
not to remember chestnut
like this.
Okay?
I see chestnut
the day i arrived.
- I see grooming chestnut.
I see a picture of a horse
just like chestnut in a book.
We passed a chestnut horse
on route 119 near
a feed store.
There was one on
a calendar at aunt ann's,
There was one
in "life" magazine
Opposite the page
of mr. Kennedy.
Okay.
O-Okay.
Can you bring everything
you've seen to your mind?
Sure.
Even if it were, uh,
an everyday object like,
uh, say shoes?
I see all
the shoes i've worn,
My mother's
and other people i've met.
You have three pairs--
One needs a new heel.
And i see the newspaper ads
and tv ads and--
Wow.
Can't you?
- This girl has
an amazing mind.
- Try teaching her math.
- Her algebra's hopeless.
- Or french.
"Why are there so many
fish in france?"
I want to
show you something.
She thinks in pictures.
That's why she does so well
when she can see the things
that are being discussed.
Like, um, biology?
Or-- Or-- Shop.
Those are concrete things.
But language or algebra?
It's just gibberish
to her.
What's that?
Do you want to see
your french fish?
"The eels ate."
"Il est."
"Eel ate."
Ils sont,
il danse, il pense.
French is full
of "eels."
And this is
what she sees.
She's an amazing
visual thinker.
- Let me work with her.
- Fine.
We have five minutes left.
Who wants to see a movie?
- All: yeah!
- All right.
J.D., Will you do
the projector?
J.D.: Okay.
All right.
Now everybody watch
very carefully
Because this one is all
about optical illusions.
Film narrator:
it comes as a distinct
shock to most people
When they realize how
limited and inaccurate
The human senses
really are.
In this house,
faces at the window
Seem to come in assorted sizes,
don't they?
- Carlock: looks like
mr. Povey, doesn't it?
But there's nothing
wrong with the faces.
It's those windows
And what they're doing
to your brain.
Carlock:
all right, here we go.
A small one
and a tall one.
- Students: oh wow.
- Uh-Huh.
Let's see if we can
even things out a bit.
- How do they do that?!
- Female student: sit down!
- Shh!
- Temple,
sit down, please.
That is the question,
isn't it?
"How did they do that?"
Hmm?
Well, that's this week's
assignment.
- I want one page,
at least.
Female student:
a full page?
- All right, two?
- Female student: no no no.
- All right, one page.
They mess with
the perspective!
That's right, temple.
And it was a room built
with distorted perspective.
But how?
Well, do you think
you could figure it out?
Maybe if you
visualized it?
And if you build one,
i'll give you extra credit.
Yeah, okay.
Girl: oh-- Hey!
Weirdo!
Does she have
to chalk the walls?
Look at her.
- I can't do it!
- I think you can, temple.
But i can't!
Oh, i know, i know.
I shouldn't shout.
But measuring perspective
didn't work!
Mm-Hmm.
- Leigh, these are the
specifications you need.
Success, temple?
No! Give me
a clue, please!
Well, you have to think
of all the features
in the room--
The walls, the floors,
the ceilings, the doors.
Got it!
Man:
you've already gone
through this right?
But as you can see,
the horses are the
exact same size.
- Wow.
And here is the room!
Wow.
Temple,
congratulations.
I think this deserves
a round of applause.
I think it deserves
a celebration.
- Students: yeah!
- Girl: woo! Woo!
Students:
five, four, three, two, one.
Now here's a question:
If i wind this up
and then let go,
Why doesn't the propeller
stay still
And the body
of the plane spin around?
Oh, that's simple.
The resistance
of the wings.
That's absolutely right.
And watch this.
With no wings
And just one plane
of resistance...
You have
a helicopter!
You're
absolutely right.
Oh, temple.
You have
a very special mind,
you know that?
You see the world in ways
that others can't,
And that's quite
an advantage.
And you know something?
If you weren't such a goof
And you developed
this talent,
You could easily
go on to college.
What would i do
at college?
Well, with your mind,
anything you wanted to.
Just pick a subject.
Cows.
- Do they have
colleges with cows?
- Yes, they do.
And horses and pigs
and goats and sheep.
Yeah, it's called
"animal husbandry."
animal husbandry.
Yeah, it deals with
the care of animals.
Really,
anything you wanted.
You could study people--
Uh, psychology.
I'd get to
understand people?
well, that's the idea.
I'll stay here.
Temple,
think of it as a door--
A door that's going to
open up onto a whole
new world for you
And all
you need to do is
decide to go through it.
- Miss grandin?
- First off,
I talked to my old teacher
dr. Carlock.
And he said i should stress
that it wasn't
That i hadn't done the work
because i had,
But i'd collected way
too much data
And backed it up with far
too many citations,
That i needed extra time
just to make it coherent.
But if you look
at these results,
You'll see that it's not
just me, but in fact
A majority of people
who become calmer when
using my machine.
And that really makes
a clear case for me
keeping it.
Oh, and i should get
a good grade.
- Did your--
- Certainly more
than a pass.
Did your previous teacher
suggest the good grade?
No, that's me.
Leave it with me.
This is very
important work!
Hmm.
You used
a control group?
They were tested
resting, seating--
Most of them got bored.
Page four.
This is excellent.
And i think it
will be a good grade.
So i keep my machine.
In that case,
i'll stay.
I would imagine
your new roommate
will want a say
In whether you
keep the machine.
That's my
squeeze machine.
- Do i have to move it?
- No.
But don't ever move it
And then i'll always
know where it is.
Okay.
It's almost time for
"the man from u.N.C.L.E."
They play it
in the rec room.
Do you want to watch
"the man from u.N.C.L.E."?
Oh! You can't watch
"the man from u.N.C.L.E."
I do.
I'd love to watch it.
Will you show me
where it is?
Yeah, sure.
Now illya kuryakin's
tryin' to open the door,
but it's locked.
Shh!
And now the floor's
sliding under the room.
Shh!
There's a big drop
to lots of spikes!
Girls: shh!
That's other kids
in the room hissing.
- Do you like
"star trek" too?
- Yes.
Who's your favorite?
Mr. Spock.
We have a lot in common.
Maybe we can watch it
on the radio.
They broadcast it
for the blind.
They do?
Let's watch it
on the radio.
You're quieter now.
Is that because you're
in your squeeze machine?
Well, i was just
getting out.
Is my voice
that different?
It is to me.
Remember, i-- I see you
through your voice.
Do you remember
a lot of voices?
Of course.
But i remember the sounds
of places too.
We're the same,
Only you have sounds
and i have pictures.
I-- I'm off to class.
i have french class.
I hate it.
It's why i'm in
my squeeze machine.
Your squeeze machine
doesn't bother me.
- Okay?
- I know. Okay.
Bonne chance.
- Huh?
- Good luck.
- Oh.
Thank you.
Excuse me.
Is this seat taken?
No.
Temple's voice: i've always
wanted to understand
the gentleness
That other people feel
by being hugged by
their mothers.
And now i've made a machine
that lets me do that.
It feels like a wire
gets reconnected,
Like something
gets repaired.
- If it wasn't
for my machine...
...i wouldn't be
standing here today.
Instead i'd be
hiding in my room
Or spinning in circles
to calm myself
Or hitting someone.
When i was younger,
i closed myself off
from people.
I didn't even speak
until i was four.
There's a highfalutin' name
for this condition: autism.
Because of my machine,
I'm able to know
the kindness and love
That have been given to me
to reach this point
in my life.
Today more than ever,
i realize i have not
walked alone.
And i thank not only
my teachers but my friends
and family as well.
As in the words
of the song from "carousel":
* when you walk
through a storm *
* hold your head up high
* and don't be afraid
of the dark *
* at the end of a storm
* is a golden sky
* and a sweet silver song
of a lark *
* walk on through
the wind *
* walk on
through the rain *
* though your dreams
be tossed *
* and blown
* walk on
* with hope
in your heart *
* and you'll never
walk alone *
* you'll never walk
alone. *
Yay!
This is my door.
It opens to another world.
Arizona state students,
gather around.
All right.
Come on, everybody.
Come on down this way.
There we go.
All right, come on in.
Here we go.
Everybody, come on.
Let's go.
- Come on in closer now.
Now gather around
so you can hear.
All right, class,
listen up.
This is don michaels.
He runs the feedlot.
Thanks, professor.
All right,
what we got here
at any one time
Is about 50, 52,000
head of cattle.
Now they gotta weigh
650 lbs to get in here.
During the three or four
months they spend here,
They'll put on
another 400 lbs
Before they move
into the big house
for slaughterin'.
While they're here fattenin' up,
we got to keep 'em healthy.
So one of the first things
we do when they come in
Off the range
is put 'em through a dip--
Get rid of any bugs.
Excuse me there, buddy.
You okay?
Uh, that's a girl.
Miss grandin.
- Miss, are you
with us, here?
I was listening
to the cattle.
Oh yeah?
Why are some mooing
more loudly than others?
I never heard
so much mooing!
Honey, i've been around
cattle all my workin' life.
About all
i can tell you is,
That just like
the female of the species,
Cattle love to yammer
and gossip...
- ...or sulk.
It's always just
one thing or the other.
- But like i was sayin'--
- Well, there must be a reason.
They're sayin' something.
Well, i reckon' you could
get dr. Doolittle
on out here.
- He probably could tell you.
While missy here
is listenin'
To what the cattle
are sayin' to each other,
Why don't you boys
step over here with me
and see a dip in action?
Now the biggest problem
you got with a dip vat
Is that cattle
can swim all right
unless they tip on over.
Then them babies'll drown
real fast on ya
Unless you get a hold of 'em
and haul 'em out.
- Well, there you go!
See, this is what
i was tellin' ya.
Jesus!
Come on, boys.
Earn your money!
- Whoa! Hold 'em up
over there!
- Hold 'em up!
Come on, boys.
We're gonna lose that baby.
Roy! Roy, get a rope
on this heifer and drag it out!
Well, there you go.
You'll see inside.
It'll take more than that
to kill a cow.
Do you lose many?
Well, we got to run
300 of 'em through here
in an hour.
I guess in a week,
we'll lose one or two maybe.
- We're doin' pretty good.
Doolittle,
how you holdin' up?
Too much for ya?
- They like to walk
in circles.
Well, what do you
know, boys?
Cattle like to walk
in circles!
Dang, give that girl
a prize.
It calms 'em down
to walk in circles
away from the handlers.
Maybe you oughta wait out here
when we go inside.
Then when we have it
in the cage,
It just takes
one knock to the head.
So, doolittle,
what do you think?
- Where does it go?
- Meat processing.
No, where does it go?
It was here,
now it's meat.
Where did it go?
Professor, i think maybe
your young lady here
Oughta consider
another line of work.
Mooing.
You want to do research
- And write your
master's on mooing.
- Curves.
Cattle like curves.
They don't moo at curves.
Miss grandin,
when we accepted you,
We were impressed
you had excelled at
your previous school.
A master's thesis
on mooing strikes me
As a lowering of the bar
and i, for one,
Will not be the first person
to give you an easy ride
Because of your autism.
- Come up with something--
- Cattle are prey animals.
My autism allows me
to understand prey
animals well.
I can visualize
the flight zones of cattle.
A handler outside
the the flight zone
Can keep an animal circling
in a calm and orderly manner.
But stepping
into the flight zone
panics the cattle.
And-- And they change
from soft moos
To loud mooing.
Like, prey animals
don't make noises
That will draw attention
to them
Unless they're trying
to warn other members
of the herd.
So they're warning
each other they're going
to be slaughtered?
No. No.
No, sir.
The-- The loud mooing
is the same
Whether they're gonna
be dipped, driven around
a hard corner
Or taken to slaughter.
They have no idea what's
gonna happen to 'em,
- I'm glad we agree on that.
- But they're spooked.
Spooked cattle
don't act straight.
They get bruised,
scraped, drowned,
And that all costs money.
And it takes a good
half hour to calm a herd
And that costs money too.
It's not a good way
to run a stockyard.
And i believe
what's good for cattle
Is also good for business.
Hmm.
Well, get the yard
to sign off on it.
You mean don.
That's who's in charge.
Sorry, ma'am.
No women on the lot.
My name
is temple grandin.
- I'm a grad student
at arizona state.
- That's the rules, ma'am.
I'm a grad student
at arizona state and i
was here last week.
Complaints
from cowboys' wives.
They just don't want
no women on the yard.
I'm just doin' my job.
Ma'am, you're holdin'
up the line.
You're going to
have to turn around and
take it on off the lot.
Please.
Cowboy:
don't come back.
John richmond, press,
"ranchman magazine."
Go on in.
Temple's voice:
it's a door.
It's another door.
Thanks, ma'am.
Take care.
- Good mornin'.
- Go on in.
- Mornin'.
Don: hi, sanch.
Good to have you
back, son.
- Seems like a long time
since you worked out here.
- Sanch: yeah, it does.
- Don: what is this,
a purple heart?
- Yeah, it is.
Don:
we're real proud of ya.
Jeez, sanch,
You didn't get all these
just diggin' latrines.
- No, sir.
I was in khe sanh.
- Good for you.
Excuse me, sir.
I need you to sign off
on my master's thesis.
- How'd you get in here?
- They just waved me in.
Well, what are you
gonna research?
- Agitation in cattle.
- Would that be mooing?
you believe that crap?
Since cattle are prey animals,
loud mooing is a sign of--
No way.
Come on, sanch,
let's get some coffee.
Say, did you bring back
one of them little china
gals with ya?
No, they wouldn't
let me bring back one
on the airplane.
Don:
you girls got the coffee
ready in here?
- We got a man
that's thirsty.
- Woman: come on in!
Do you have
another entrance?
Pardon?
Do you have
another entrance?
No, ma'am.
Do you have any jell-O
or yogurt?
In the cooler.
Right behind you, darlin'.
Narrator on tv:
by eating the weaker
and slower ones,
Lions keep
the antelope population
Strong and in proper
proportion
To all other animals.
Light.
Shadow.
- Reflections on puddle.
I've eaten
bulls' testicles!
Ate 'em
in my aunt's ranch...
- Regularly!
This is a waste!
hey!
You gotta remember
to drink out here.
Well, i have data on things
that make 'em balk--
Like shadows,
Reflections on water,
or chain glinting
in the sun.
- Is that right?
- They won't walk
into shaded areas.
They need to see
where they're goin'.
I've lots of important
information on all this
And i need mr. Michaels
to sign off on it.
Don? Don don't
sign nothin'.
- I need mr. Michaels--
- You're not hearin' me.
Don don't sign nothin'.
I sign everything
around here.
His signature,
but i do the signin'.
I'm not even sure
if don can write.
Say, uh, you're
interested in cattle
and how cattle act,
You shouldn't just
hang around feedlots.
You should be
out on ranches,
auctions, rodeos,
That sort of thing.
Auctioneer:
got the big steer here.
1,000 lbs.
Let's go! 20. 25.
25 and a half.
- 25 and a half, 75.
He's 25 and a half, 75.
- He looks mean.
25, 65. 75 75. 30 30 30 30.
Sold him on pat 17.
Look at his mama here.
Now, 75, i got 25.
25 25 25.
27 and a half.
He's 27 and a half. 30.
32 and a half. 35.
Sold 'em.
Pat 21. Pat 21.
Yeah, it's a good magazine.
I'd like you to take
a look at--
Help you out with
all kinds of cattle questions.
See you back here
in about five minutes, okay?
Excuse--
It's all doors
to new worlds.
Excuse me, sir?
Sir?
I'm very pleased
to meet you.
I'm temple grandin,
a bachelor of science
Doin' my masters here
at arizona state,
Currently studying
in scottsdale feed yards
And i was wondering
if i could interest
"The arizona farmer-
Ranchman" periodical
on a thesis i'm writing
On control systems
and cattle
And why some work
better than others
And how they can tell
the difference.
How'd you get on
with old don michaels
over at scottsdale?
I told him i've eaten
bull testicles, sir.
Well, i will read anything
you send in, miss grandin.
In fact, here--
Take my card.
You address it
directly to me.
Thank you, sir.
Thank you!
It's open.
Sir, scottsdale feedlot
signed off
On my cattle
agitation study.
Smells like half the herd
signed it first.
- No, sir.
Cattle can't do that.
And i don't
need the magazine.
I'm a subscriber.
Oh, well, i just
wanted to make sure
you saw my article
On mooing as a guide
to cattle agitation.
Full thesis is still
at the typist,
- But you should
have it by friday.
- Temple?
* silver bells
* silver bells...
Temple!
Well,
master of science.
Master of science
and animal science.
Fantastic.
I'll bet you're glad
to be back east.
- I like the west.
- Oh, so do i,
But it isn't home,
is it?
What will you do
with your masters?
Your mother mentioned
teaching maybe.
Great new school
over west medford way.
I have a lot of more research
to do and things to write.
That's right,
you've been published.
You remember scott?
- Scott?
Scotty, over here.
- I'll be right back.
- He's our oldest boy.
"New york" magazine's
taken a piece of his.
You remember scott?
He used to spit
in my jell-O.
Oh, i'm sure
he didn't.
temple, tell scott
about your writing.
Published two articles
In "the arizona
farmer-Ranchman."
- "The arizona"--
- "The arizona
farmer-Ranchman."
One was on good moos
and bad moos.
The other was
on head restraints
And cattle chutes
and killing pens.
They're really
badly designed.
Just terrible systems.
- Just--
- Wow.
It's lovely
to see you, temple.
- Bye.
- Merry christmas.
Merry christmas!
I need my squeeze machine!
I hate parties.
There are too many people
and no one listens to me.
And they keep giving
each other looks
And i don't know
what they mean.
They're just
uncomfortable.
People don't want
to hear all those
details about cattle.
Well, i do.
I wanna be with cattle.
Sweetheart,
i don't want you
to avoid people.
- They make me feel bad.
- Then ignore them.
You are the only
master of science
in the room.
And i am so
proud of you.
Temple, look at me.
Look at me.
Do you know if people
tell each other things
with their eyes,
This is me telling you
that i love you and
i respect you?
I will never learn
how to do that.
I know.
Hey!
Damn it!
You are not
allowed in here.
- I'm doin' research
for an article.
- No, ma'am.
We put up with you
sneakin' in here
When you was at arizona state,
but you're done with that.
No college,
no insurance coverage,
no access.
There are many other
articles i would like
to write for you.
Firstly, how cattle can be
introduced into dip vats
on their own accord.
- Secondly--
- H-Hold on,
miss grandin.
Firstly,
your articles have
been greatly appreciated.
I got a lot of calls.
Folks think
you talk sense.
Secondly, i told you
i would read anything
that you write.
Thirdly, young lady,
you need another
set of clothes
When you come
into town on business.
I need to be an
accredited press person.
C-Can i get
a press pass?
You askin'
for a staff job?
I ain't got but four staff,
and-- And two of them
Are bookkeeping
and distribution.
No, i don't wanna
work here.
I wanna be with cattle,
so i need a pass.
W-Well,
we can do that.
But like i said--
Mary-Anne?
Get in here.
Sir?
How's that workin'
for ya, miss grandin?
It doesn't itch.
I like it a lot.
That's my rank.
They'll be able
to see that.
- Hey, what--
Damn it!
Use it, temple.
You stink.
- Thank you.
- Temple?
Miss temple grandin?
I'm ted gilbert,
from john wayne's
red river feedlot.
Hello, i'm very pleased
to meet you.
Hell, i've been
reading your stuff.
How'd you like to
put it into practice?
See, i lost my designer
And, uh, i need
a new cattle dip.
Can you do it?
It's pretty simple, but,
uh, i got to present
plans in five days.
Sure!
This is very clever.
How did you come up with this?
I just see things
and put 'em together.
- So how long
will it take ya to--
- And all this?
That's to lead
the cattle in.
They're happy to follow
a curve 'cause they think
- They're goin' back
to where they came from.
- If you say so.
Well, i do.
So h-How long will it
take you to do it?
Well, i have two or three
more before this.
- But i need it by tomorrow!
- Everybody needs it tomorrow.
- I won't work any quicker
with you watching.
- I wanna watch.
Okay.
Ted:
hey, temple?
This here is red harris
from "cattle magazine."
Very nice to meet you,
mr. Harris.
Yeah, well, red,
he can't make the grand
opening tomorrow,
So i thought we'd give him
a sneak preview.
So, temple, will you
put some cattle through
your dip while i'm here?
Okay.
Hey,
open the gate!
So if the handlers
walk slowly clockwise
outside the chute,
Then the cow will
walk counterclockwise
through the chute.
See? They'll just follow
that curve.
The cattle just keep
calmly walking
Thinking they're goin' in
circles and followin'
their buddies.
And they're happy
to follow a curve
Because they think
they're going' back
To where
they came from.
They're okay because
it's grooved
And they know
they won't slip.
So when they take the next step,
their center of gravity
Makes them drop
calmly into the dip
And they just walk
through the water.
Red:
i don't usually tell people
what i'm gonna write,
But, miss grandin,
this is a masterpiece.
- Hey.
- I don't want
to do that.
I'm sorry there,
temple.
Now, look, i want you to be
dressed in your best outfit
tomorrow mornin', okay?
Okay.
Just look at this thing.
It'll take us forever
to get them through here.
J.D., I want you to get
the torch and red,
And i want this out,
this out,
I want those panels lined up
And we're gonna run
'em straight in.
Come on, boys.
You two come with me.
- Grab the other end of this.
- Now hold on!
Look at this!
I mean, look at that!
Who'd build
somethin' like that?
Jess, get me
some sheet steel.
We're gonna slide
these puppies in here.
- Where's that sheet steel?
- Hurry up!
Let's go.
Get up.
- Put 'em over in that pile
and get 'em out of here.
- She's here.
Don't keep worried, boys.
I'll take care of her.
Pick it up.
Some dip you got here.
Who put steel
on that slope?
Cattle can't walk
on steel!
That's designed
so they'll walk slowly!
'Scuse me, little miss.
We just had three head
drown in here.
That's your fault!
You killed 'em 'cause
of your stupidity!
And why ain't they comin'
through the curved chute?
That'd take us
all day little lady!
Hey, that's my shirt!
If it's smooth,
they'll follow it!
If there's stuff on it,
they'll get scared!
You can't hang things!
- You wacko!
- Put it all back
the way it was!
Ted:
temple, what's goin' on here?
They killed three cattle
because of their stupidity!
They ruined it!
- Carlock: just a minute!
- Cattle aren't dangerous!
- Temple?
And they're predictable.
So it's not hard to
design a system
- That won't hurt 'em!
- What are you doing
in california?
But the cowboys would rather
prod 'em and scare 'em.
Did you drive
all night?
I designed a dip vat
at john red river feedlot
Based on the way cattle see
and think and behave
And the editor
of "cattle magazine"
Said it was a masterpiece
but the cowboys
Killed three cows in it--
- Three...
- Uh-Huh.
...in five minutes
Because they wouldn't
follow my design!
Temple, would you like
to sit down, or--
- I can't protect the cattle...
- I'm having a cut of tea.
Would you like to join me?
...unless i design
the whole system from
the moment they enter
To the moment
they get slaughtered.
Are you talking about
a slaughterhouse?
Well, of course
they're gonna get
slaughtered.
Do you think we'd
have cattle if people
didn't eat 'em every day?
They'd just be funny-Lookin'
animals in zoos.
No, we raise them for us.
That means we owe them
some respect.
Nature is cruel,
but we don't have to be.
I wouldn't want
to have my guts
ripped out by a lion.
I'd much rather die
in a slaughterhouse
if it was done right!
It seems to me
that you should be
the one--
Well, we can easily
do it in a way
Where they don't feel pain
and they don't get scared.
And their cortisol levels
go through the roof!
Okay. Did you hear what
i said, temple? I think
you're the one
- Who should design
the slaughterhouse.
- Yeah, well, i'm going--
I know a slaughterhouse
that's a mess and i know
exactly how to fix it.
Hmm.
It's a door.
It's another door.
Can i help you?
Hello, it's very nice
to meet you.
I'd like to tour
your slaughterhouse.
Excuse me?
Hello, it's very nice
to meet you.
I'd like to tour
your slaughterhouse.
We don't do tours,
ma'am.
I designed a drip vat
at john wayne's
red river feedlot
That the editor
of "cattle magazine"
said was a masterpiece--
Security?
Can i get security
to the front office?
Eustacia: temple, i'm so sorry
to leave this message on
your answering machine,
But i thought
you'd want to know
That your friend
dr. Carlock has died.
Well, i just saw him!
Apparently, he'd been
sick for some time.
You can call me anytime.
Bye, sweetheart.
I just saw him.
What are they doing?
They're paying
their respects.
It's a way of saying
thank you and goodbye.
I said goodbye
when i saw him.
This is a final chance
to say goodbye.
Temple.
- Are you all right?
- I'm leaving now.
Well--
It isn't over yet.
I said goodbye
when i saw him.
He's not there.
Ah.
I've got him
in my mind.
Do you know
where they go?
No.
No, i don't.
Okay.
I'm gonna go now.
Drive safely.
Clerk:
there you are, ma'am.
My, that's
a pretty blouse.
I hope you don't mind
me sayin' so.
Some people think
i'm forward,
But, you know,
if i like somethin',
I just come right out
and just compliment 'em.
it's nice to get
a compliment,
Don't you think?
Thank you.
It's very nice to meet you.
I'm temple grandin.
Well, uh-- I--
It's nice to meet you too.
I'm betty.
Well then,
there we are.
Are you waitin' to meet
somebody or somethin'?
No, i have trouble
with automatic doors
sometimes when i'm nervous.
I'm autistic.
Oh.
My son is artistic
and he's got the same
thing with airplanes.
Oh, come on.
You just come
along with me.
All right.
Come on.
And-- And i'll make sure
that they stay open.
All right?
You are safe now.
You're safe.
- Thank you.
- My pleasure.
are you a horsewoman?
I mean,
you know, your shirt?
Well, i like horses,
but i work with cattle.
I designed a dip
that "cattle magazine"
called brilliant.
Oh my golly,
my husband read
about you.
He works over at abbot.
- Abbot slaughterhouse?
- Yeah.
- You heard of it?
- Well, i wanna redesign it.
I went there,
but they wouldn't
let me meet with them.
But i have several ideas
about how to make a new facility
That will be much more
humane and efficient.
Well, i guess you just have
to meet my husband then.
How wonderful that we
bumped into each other.
A door opened
and i went through it.
Yes, you did.
And i held it.
This looks like
an airport for cows.
- Thank you.
I didn't mean that
as a compliment.
And conveyor belts
for cattle?
- Do you have any idea
what the cost is on this?
And you've got
solid walls and floors.
We have those slatted
for a reason.
- It's cheaper.
- I'm sorry, miss grandin.
It's clear you just don't
have the experience
To design something
like this.
The walls are solid
so the cattle
Won't be distracted by light
or movement outside.
They balk
at unexpected things.
I'm sure that's
nice for the cattle,
but the cost, miss--
How much money
does it cost you
To pay handlers to prod
the cattle along
And then hold 'em back
when they stampede?
How many times a day
do your chutes stop
because of pile-Ups?
How many cows break a leg
and bring everything to a halt?
With my system,
there'd be none of that.
There'd be
a steady calm flow.
Well, that sounds great,
but you don't have any idea
of whether it'll work.
But i do.
I'm like nikola tesla
or thomas edison--
I know my system will work
'cause i've been through it
A thousand times
in my head.
I can see a chute
just as the cattle will
Because that's something
my autism lets me do.
I can walk through
a plan in my mind,
Examining every beam
and every rivet.
I mean,
you just see a plan,
But i'm walkin' through
the whole plant.
Okay, the cattle go through
a series of solid curves.
The floor is solid too--
Grooved.
The chute gets smaller,
but the cattle won't mind.
They don't-- They don't
see any danger.
They think they're just
gettin' into another truck.
The stairway leads
them gently upwards.
The floor becomes
a conveyor.
A rest rises up to meet
their chest
So they're
comfortably carried.
They'll be very calm.
Nature is cruel,
but we don't have to be.
We owe them some respect.
I touched the first cow
as it was being stunned.
In a few seconds,
it was gonna be just
another piece of beef, but...
- ...in that moment,
it was still an individual.
It was calm
And then it was gone.
I became aware
of how precious life was.
And i thought about death
and i felt close to god.
I don't want my thoughts
to die with me.
I want to have
done something.
Thank you
for inviting me.
You were the one person
i wanted here.
Other people would have
been overwhelmed by what
they were seeing.
It would have
confused them.
I knew you would be
the only one
Able to sense
what was really going on,
Who could feel what
i was trying to accomplish.
I know there are a lot
of things i can't understand,
But i still want my life
to have meaning.
I don't know
that i want to hear
from any more experts.
- Expert: if you will
please let me finish.
Will you please
let me finish?
With intensive psychotherapy,
an autistic child
can be treated--
Woman:
but the rimland report
plainly shows
That autism is not a
psychological problem.
Expert:
i am not familiar
with the rimland report.
Calm down.
Calm done, sweetie.
Sweetie, calm down.
Calm down.
Expert: it would be better
if you could get her
to sit calmly.
Try to control her.
Man ã‚â£2:
but we were told
self-Stimming is good.
It eventually calms them.
Woman:
self-Stimming
is self-Comforting.
Man ã‚â£2:
self-Stimulation--
Rocking, spinning,
Rolling on the floor,
flapping the--
Well, i think
spinning is good.
And rolling too.
Self-Stimulation does
seem to eventually calm
the nervous system.
It can be a way
to compensate for
not being held.
And being held
by another person is scary,
But rolling
or being held by surfaces
Produces the calming effect
that ordinary children
get from a hug.
Woman ã‚â£2:
how old's your child?
Well, i don't have
children.
- No, i'm autistic.
And i need the sensation
of being hugged.
And i've developed
a machine that i get into
And hugs me
and i'm different afterwards.
I'm more social.
Well, i didn't speak
until i was four
And now i have a b.A.
And a masters
And i'm studying
for my doctorate.
- Please don't shout!
Please!
Uh, most autistic people
are very sensitive
To sounds and colors.
Over-Stimulation hurts.
You know, people talkin'
too much at once, you know,
can cause us to panic.
Man ã‚â£3:
how did you get cured?
Well, i'm not cured.
I'll always be autistic.
My mother refused to believe
that i wouldn't speak.
And when i learned to speak,
she made me go to school.
And in school
and at home,
Manners and rules
were really important.
They were pounded
into me.
I was lucky.
All these things
worked for me.
Everyone worked hard
to make sure that i
was engaged.
I mean, they knew
i was different,
but not less.
You know,
i had a gift.
I could see the world
in a new way.
I could see details
that other people
were blind to.
My mother pushed me
to become self-Sufficient.
I worked summers
at my aunt's ranch.
I went to boarding school
and college
And those things w-Were
uncomfortable for me at first,
But they helped me
to open doors to new worlds.
Woman:
excuse me, please,
But we want to hear
everything.
- Man: yes.
- Woman: please.
Temple's voice:
are you a scientist?
Mr. Peters' voice:
you cannot hit people.
Dr. Carlock's voice:
think you can figure it out?
Students' voices:
five, four, three, two, one.
Temple's voice:
i have a pen and a clipboard.
Carlock's voice:
think of it as a door.
Don's voice:
just take one knock
to the head.
Temple's voice:
i don't understand
Why people are cruel
for no reason!
Carlock's voice:
you have a very special mind.
You see the world in ways
that others can't.
Red harris's voice:
miss grandin, this is
a masterpiece.
Temple's voice:
a door opened and i
went through it.
Betty's voice:
yes, you did,
And i held it.
I'm temple grandin.